<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<topic xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="A01_topic_1"
       xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:nccer:names:ncs:xsd:NCS_topic.xsd"
       xml:lang="en">
   <supertitle>Plumbing Level One</supertitle>
   <title>Module 02101</title>
   <prolog/>
   <body>
      <p>Trainee Guide</p>
      <p>
         <b>NCCER</b>
      </p>
      <p>
         <i>Chief Executive Officer:</i> Don Whyte</p>
      <p>
         <i>President:</i> Boyd Worsham</p>
      <p>
         <i>Chief Operations Officer:</i> Katrina Kersch</p>
      <p>
         <i>Plumbing Curriculum Project Manager:</i> John Esbenshade</p>
      <p>
         <i>Director, Product Development:</i> Tim Davis</p>
      <p>
         <i>Senior Production Manager:</i> Erin O'Nora</p>
      <p>
         <i>Senior Manager of Projects:</i> Chris Wilson</p>
      <p>
         <i>Desktop Publishing Manager:</i> James McKay</p>
      <p>
         <i>Managing Editor:</i> Graham Hack</p>
      <p>
         <i>Art Manager:</i> Kelly Sadler</p>
      <p>
         <i>Multimedia Project Manager</i>: Alan Youngblood</p>
      <p>
         <i>Digital Content Coordinator:</i> Rachael Downs</p>
      <p>
         <i>Production Specialists:</i> Gene Page, Eric Caraballoso</p>
      <p>
         <i>Production Assistance:</i> Adrienne Payne, David Gregoire, Edward Fortman, Joanne Hart,
         Olga Trofymenko</p>
      <p>
         <i>Editors:</i> Jordan Hutchinson, Karina Kuchta</p>
      <p>
         <b>Pearson</b>
      </p>
      <p>
         <i>Director of Alliance/Partnership Management:</i> Kelly Trakalo</p>
      <p>
         <i>Content Producer:</i> Alexandrina B. Wolf</p>
      <p>
         <i>Assistant Content Producer:</i> Alma Dabral</p>
      <p>
         <i>Digital Content Producer:</i> Jose Carchi</p>
      <p>
         <i>Senior Marketing Manager:</i> Brian Hoehl</p>
      <p>
         <i>Composition: </i>NCCER</p>
      <p>
         <i>Content Technologies:</i> Gnostyx</p>
      <p>Credits and acknowledgments for content borrowed from other sources and reproduced, with permission, in this textbook appear at the end of each module. </p>
      <p sourcetype="copyright">
         <b>Copyright © 2020, 2012, 2005, 2001, 1998 by NCCER, Alachua, FL 32615, and published by
            Pearson, New York, NY 10013. All rights reserved.</b> Printed in the United States of
         America. This publication is protected by Copyright and permission should be obtained from
         NCCER prior to any prohibited reproduction, storage in a retrieval system, or transmission
         in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording, or likewise.
         For information regarding permission(s), write to: NCCER Product Development, 13614
         Progress Blvd., Alachua, FL 32615.</p>
      <p>10 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1</p>
      <p>ISBN-13:978-0-13-021010-0</p>
      <p>ISBN-10:0-13-021010-X</p>
      <section>
         <title>NCCER Standardized Curricula</title>
         <p>NCCER is a not-for-profit 501(c)(3) education foundation established in 1996 by the world’s largest and most progressive construction companies and national construction associations. It was founded to address the severe workforce shortage facing the industry and to develop a standardized training process and curricula. Today, NCCER is supported by hundreds of leading construction and maintenance companies, manufacturers, and national associations. The NCCER Standardized Curricula was developed by NCCER in partnership with Pearson, the world’s largest educational publisher.</p>
         <p>Some features of the NCCER Standardized Curricula are as follows:</p>
         <ul>
            <li>
               <p>An industry-proven record of success</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Curricula developed by the industry for the industry</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>National standardization providing portability of learned job skills and educational credits</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Compliance with the Office of Apprenticeship requirements for related classroom training (<i>CFR 29:29</i>)</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Well-illustrated, up-to-date, and practical information</p>
            </li>
         </ul>
         <p>NCCER also maintains the NCCER Registry, which provides transcripts, certificates, and wallet cards to individuals who have successfully completed a level of training within a craft in NCCER’s Curricula. <i>Training programs must be delivered by an NCCER Accredited Training Sponsor in order to receive these credentials</i>.</p>
         <p>For information on NCCER’s credentials and the NCCER Registry, contact NCCER Customer Service at 1-888-622-3720 or visit <xref href="http://www.nccer.org" format="html" scope="external">www.nccer.org</xref>.</p>
         <p>Our website, <xref href="http://www.nccer.org" format="html" scope="external"
               >www.nccer.org</xref>, has information on the latest product releases and
            training.</p>
         <p>Your feedback is welcome. You may email your comments to <xref href="mailto:curriculum@nccer.org" format="html" scope="external">curriculum@nccer.org</xref> or send general comments and inquiries to <xref href="mailto:info@nccer.org" format="html" scope="external">info@nccer.org</xref>.</p>
      </section>
   </body>
</topic>
