<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><learningContent xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="M01_topic_2_1_3" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:nccer:names:ncs:xsd:NCS_learningContent.xsd" xml:lang="en">
   <title>1.1.3 Plumbing in the Twentieth Century</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <lcInstruction>
         <p>Sanitation, along with medical science, continues to be largely responsible for the maintenance of public health. In the United States, great progress in the development of plumbing methods and technologies has been made since 1910. The reliability of traditional piping materials, such as copper and cast iron, has been dramatically improved. A new plastic compound called <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/thermoplastic">thermoplastic</term> (which is soft and pliable when heated) and <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/thermoset">thermoset</term> (which becomes solid when heated) have been developed. The physical properties of these plastics make them ideal for use in sanitary systems. <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/polyvinyl_chloride_pvc">Polyvinyl chloride (PVC)</term>, developed in the 1930s, was the first plastic used in plumbing. PVC is a rigid pipe with high-impact strength that is manufactured from a thermoplastic material. The material has an indefinite life span under most conditions. Plumbers frequently use PVC in cold water systems. Manufacturers have also improved plumbing <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/fixtures">fixtures</term>, which are devices that receive water from a water supply line. Common fixtures include sinks, faucets, shower stalls, and toilets.</p>
      </lcInstruction>
      <section>
         <p>In 1911, the Kohler Company developed the first one-piece recessed bath. Before this, baths had been built in two separate sections: the tub itself and the surrounding apron. Kohler’s one-piece tub was much more sanitary and attractive. In 1926, Kohler introduced the electric sink, a combination of a conventional sink and electric dishwasher.</p>
         <p>Other inventors established companies whose names are familiar to today’s plumbers. Al Moen, who held more than 75 patents, invented the single-handle mixing faucet. In 1906, William Sloan developed a flush valve in which water flows under pressure from the supply pipe directly to the fixture, so that it is always ready to be used. Halsey W. Taylor established the company that bears his name in 1912 to manufacture and sell hygienic drinking fountains.</p>
      </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>