<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningContent xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="M01_topic_2_2_2"
   xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:nccer:names:ncs:xsd:NCS_learningContent.xsd" xml:lang="en">
   <title>1.2.2 What is Plumbing?</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <lcInstruction>
         <p>Plumbing has different meanings to different people. The National Standard Plumbing Code
            (NSPC) defines plumbing as follows:</p>
      </lcInstruction>
      <ul>
         <li>
            <p>The practice, materials, and fixtures within or adjacent to any building structure or
               conveyance, used in the installation, maintenance, extension, alteration, and removal
               of all piping, plumbing fixtures, plumbing appliances, and plumbing <term
                  keyref="M01_trade_definitions/appurtenances">appurtenances</term> (accessories
               that don’t require water supply or add a load to the waste side) connected with the
               following:</p>
            
            <p>a. sanitary drainage systems and related vent systems;</p>
         
            <p>b. storm water drainage facilities and venting systems;</p>
        
            <p>c. public or private potable water supply systems;</p>
        
            <p>d. the initial connection to a potable water supply upstream of any required <term
                  keyref="M01_trade_definitions/backflow">backflow</term> prevention devices (which
               prevent nonpotable water from entering the potable supply system) and the final
               connection that discharges indirectly into a public or private disposal system;</p>
         
            <p>e. medical gas and medical vacuum systems;</p>
         
            <p>f. indirect waste piping, including refrigeration and air conditioning drainage; and</p>
        
            <p>g. liquid waste or sewage, and water supply, of any premises to their connection with
               the approved water supply system or to an acceptable disposal facility.</p>
         </li>

      </ul>
      
      <section>
         <p>Both the <i>International Plumbing Code (IPC)</i> and the <i>Uniform Plumbing Code
               (UPC)</i> define plumbing as:</p>
      </section>
      <ul>
         <li>
            <p>The practice, materials and fixtures utilized in the installation, maintenance,
               extension and alteration of all piping, fixtures, plumbing appliances and plumbing
               appurtenances, within or adjacent to any structure, in connection with sanitary
               drainage or storm drainage facilities; venting systems; and public or private water
               supply systems.</p>
         </li>
      </ul>
      <section>
         <p>You can see that these definitions largely cover the same range of activities, although
            the NSPC definition is more specific in including medical gas and vacuum systems and
            refrigeration and air conditioning drainage systems.</p>
      </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>
