<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<topic xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="M01_topic_4_3"
       xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:nccer:names:ncs:xsd:NCS_topic.xsd"
       xml:lang="en"
       sourcetype="appendix">
   <supertitle>Appendix A</supertitle>
   <body>
      <section>
         <title>Ethical Principles for Members of the Construction Trades</title>
      
         <dl>
            <dlentry>
               <dt>Honesty:</dt>
               <dd>Be honest and truthful in all dealings. Conduct business according to the highest professional standards. Faithfully fulfill all contracts and commitments. Do not deliberately mislead or deceive others.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
               <dt>Integrity:</dt>
               <dd>Demonstrate personal integrity and the courage of your convictions by doing what is right even where there is pressure to do otherwise. Do not sacrifice your principles because it seems easier.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
               <dt>Loyalty:</dt>
               <dd>Be worthy of trust. Demonstrate fidelity and loyalty to companies, employers, sponsors, co-workers, and trade institutions and organizations.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
               <dt>Fairness:</dt>
               <dd>Be fair and just in all dealings. Do not take undue advantage of another’s mistakes or difficulties. Fair people are open-minded and committed to justice, equal treatment of individuals, and tolerance for and acceptance of diversity.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
               <dt>Respect for others:</dt>
               <dd>Be courteous and treat all people with equal respect and dignity.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
               <dt>Obedience:</dt>
               <dd>Abide by laws, rules, and regulations relating to all personal and business activities.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
               <dt>Commitment to excellence:</dt>
               <dd>Pursue excellence in performing your duties, be well informed and prepared, and constantly try to increase your proficiency by gaining new skills and knowledge.</dd>
            </dlentry>
            <dlentry>
               <dt>Leadership:</dt>
               <dd>By your own conduct, seek to be a positive role model for others.</dd>
            </dlentry>
         </dl>
      </section>
   </body>
</topic>