<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningContent xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="M01_topic_3_2_1"
   xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:nccer:names:ncs:xsd:NCS_learningContent.xsd" xml:lang="en">
   <title>2.2.1 Formal Construction Training</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <lcInstruction>
         <p>The Department of Labor’s Office of Apprenticeship sets the minimum standards for
            training programs across the country. Office of Apprenticeship programs rely on
            mandatory classroom instruction and OJL. Office of Apprenticeship requires 144 hours of
            classroom instruction per year and 2,000 hours of OJL per year. In a typical Office of
            Apprenticeship program, trainees spend 576 hours in classroom instruction and 8,000
            hours in OJL before receiving journey plumber certificates.</p>
      </lcInstruction>
      <section>
         <p>To address the training needs of the professional communities, NCCER developed a
            four-year plumbing training program. NCCER uses the minimum Office of Apprenticeship
            standards as a foundation for comprehensive curricula that provide trainees with
            in-depth classroom and OJL experience.</p>
         <p>The primary goal of NCCER is to standardize construction craft training throughout the
            country so that employers and employees benefit from it, no matter where they are
            located. As a trainee in an NCCER program, you receive benefits to help you prepare for
            your career in the plumbing profession. You will become part of the National Registry.
            You will receive a certificate for each level of training you complete. If you apply for
            a job with any participating contractor in the country, a transcript of your training
            will be available for that contractor to help verify your qualifications. If your
            training is incomplete when you make a job transfer, you can pick up where you left off,
            because every participating training center is using the same program. Many technical
            schools and colleges also use this program.</p>
         <p>The NCCER Plumbing curriculum provides trainees with industry-driven training and
            education. It adopts a purely competency-based teaching philosophy. This means that
            trainees must demonstrate to the instructor that they possess the understanding and the
            skills necessary to complete the tasks that are covered in each module before they can
            advance to the next stage of the curriculum.</p>
         <p>When the instructor is satisfied that a trainee has successfully demonstrated the
            required knowledge and skills for a particular module, test scores and completion
            information are sent to NCCER and kept in the National Registry. The National Registry
            can then confirm training and skills for workers as they move from state to state,
            company to company, or even within a company (see <xref href="M01_topic_4_4.xml">Appendix B</xref>).</p>
         <p>Whether you enroll in an NCCER program or another Office of Apprenticeship-approved
            program, ensure that you work for an employer or sponsor who supports a nationally
            standardized training program that includes credentials to confirm your skill
            development.</p>
         <p>A good apprenticeship program effectively combines competency-based, hands-on training
            with classroom instruction. This combination is the most effective way for a beginning
            plumber to learn and advance through the plumbing profession. Successful apprentices
            will develop the skills and knowledge they need to carry out a wide range of tasks.</p>
         <p>If you possess these professional and personal skills, you can become a top-notch,
            highly productive journey plumber. Journey plumbers have successfully completed an
            apprenticeship-training program. The term comes from the fifteenth-century word
            journeyman. Journeymen were apprentices who left their masters after learning their
            craft and worked alone or for someone else.</p>
         <p>Successful journey plumbers who practice their craft with pride and skill are valued
            employees and co-workers. Once you have mastered the professional and personal skills
            necessary, you will be a good candidate to advance to an exciting and challenging career
            as a master plumber, superintendent plumber, plumbing supervisor, instructor, inspector,
            project manager, or contractor and business owner.</p>
      </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>
