<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learningContent xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="M01_topic_3_2"
   xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:nccer:names:ncs:xsd:NCS_learningContent.xsd" xml:lang="en">
   <title>2.2.0 Career Opportunities in Plumbing</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <lcInstruction>
         <p>The construction industry employs more people and contributes more to the nation’s
            economy than any other industry. Our society will always need people to build new homes,
            roads, airports, hospitals, schools, factories, and office buildings, maintain existing
            structures, and replace old and damaged ones. This means there will always be a source
            of well-paying jobs and career opportunities for construction trade professionals,
            including plumbers. Both large and small contracting firms employ plumbers. Plumbers who
            master the principles of small-business management and develop and hone their
            entrepreneurial skills can be self-employed.</p>
      </lcInstruction>
      <section>
         <p>Plumbers can choose from a number of career paths depending on their skills and
            interests (see <xref href="#M01_topic_3_2/M01_02101-18_TG-figure3">Figure 3</xref>).
            Where you go depends on the pride and professionalism you show in your work. How well
            you succeed depends on your willingness to develop your skills and obtain the right
            training. With time and experience, plumbers progress from apprentices to one or more
            different specialties. These are some of the many positions and careers in the plumbing
            profession. Note that the career paths shown in <xref
               href="#M01_topic_3_2/M01_02101-18_TG-figure3">Figure 3</xref> are examples; your path
            may end up being different from those shown.</p>
      </section>
      <fig id="M01_02101-18_TG-figure3">
         <title>Figure 3 Opportunities in the construction industry.</title>
         <image keyref="02101-18_F03">
            <alt>Opportunities in the construction industry. Chart shows management and craft that
               consists of apprenticeship (3-5 years), technical college (2 years), college
               apprenticeship (2-5 years), university (4 years). With an apprenticeship and
               technical college (2 years) you can go from journeyman plumber, master plumber,
               superintendent plumber, and move to plumbing instructor. As a plumbing inspector you
               can move to project manager which is located in the management section that requires
               college apprenticeship and university. From foreman/ lead man you can move to
               plumbing superintendent, project manager, administrator business management to CEO/
               Company Owner. With a 4 year university degree- bachelor's degree construction
               management architecture engineering, masters degree construction management
               architecture engineering, doctorate construction management architecture
               engineering.</alt>
         </image>
      </fig>
      <section>
         <p>An apprentice is someone who is learning the plumbing trade. As you have learned, when a
            plumber successfully completes an apprenticeship, he or she becomes a journey plumber.
            Journey plumbers can remain at that level or advance in the profession. Journey plumbers
            might supervise less experienced plumbers or be called on to estimate the materials and
            labor for a specific job. With larger companies and on larger jobs, journey plumbers
            often become specialists.</p>
         <p>Foremen are leaders who direct a single team of apprentices and/or journey plumbers.
            Large construction projects with more than one team require supervisors who oversee the
            work of all teams. They are responsible for assigning, directing, and inspecting the
            work of each team.</p>
         <p>A master craftsman is someone who consistently demonstrates the highest level of skill
            at a profession. Master plumbers are proven experts in the plumbing profession. They can
            act as mentors and teachers to less experienced members of the profession. Master
            plumbers often start their own businesses, no matter what role they play.</p>
         <p>The safety manager is another key, on-site person. Safety managers are responsible for
            the safety and health of the workers on a project. They are responsible for developing a
            safety plan and procedures, training workers in safety procedures, and ensuring that the
            project is in compliance with applicable health and safety regulations.</p>
         <p>Project managers, often called project administrators, control the scope and direction
            of a plumbing business. Managers ensure that the right workers are being assigned to
            each task and are responsible for handling project finances. Large contracting firms may
            have several project managers.</p>
         <p>Plumbing estimators work for contractors and building supply companies. They assess the
            materials and labor required to complete a project and contractors submit bids for jobs
            based on these estimates. Plumbing estimators must have a thorough understanding of
            construction methods as well as knowledge of the availability and prices of materials
            and supplies.</p>
         <p>Plumbing estimators are experienced plumbers with superior mathematical abilities and
            the patience to prepare detailed, accurate estimates. Today’s estimators also need solid
            computer skills. Estimators have a great deal of responsibility, because errors in
            estimates can cost the contractor significant amounts of money. Depending on the size
            and type of the business, the estimating job may also be done by the contractor or the
            project manager.</p>
         <p>Mechanical engineers research, develop, design, manufacture, and test a wide range of
            mechanical devices, including the following:</p>
      </section>
      <ul>
         <li>
            <p>Machine tools</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Internal combustion engines</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Electric generators</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Steam and gas turbines</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Refrigeration and air conditioning equipment</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Material-handling systems</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Elevators and escalators</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Industrial production equipment</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Robots used in manufacturing</p>
         </li>
      </ul>
      <section>
         <p>Construction contractors and owners establish and run contracting businesses. Typically,
            they hire apprentices, journey plumbers, and master plumbers. Depending on the size of
            their business, contractors may work with the crew or may manage the business full-time.
            Small contractors may have only one or two employees who manage the business, prepare
            estimates, obtain supplies, and perform the actual contracted work. Subcontractors and
            contractors/owners may specialize in installing particular systems, such as sprinkler
            systems, high-pressure pipe systems, or municipal water-treatment facilities.</p>
         <p>Plumbing inspectors may work for a contractor or for a municipal jurisdiction such as a
            local or state government. Inspectors ensure that all plumbing installations follow
            applicable codes and quality requirements. Plumbing inspectors review and approve work
            at various stages of construction, depending on the installation.</p>
         <p>Plumbing instructors train apprentices to become the next generation of journey and
            master plumbers, managers, inspectors, and engineers. Many dedicated and experienced
            plumbers find that becoming an instructor is a natural evolution in their career. Master
            plumbers often become instructors as their careers progress.</p>
         <p>No matter what career path you choose, you will be embarking on a lifelong learning
            process. Effective plumbers along any career path need to keep up-to-date with new
            tools, materials, and methods. If you choose to become a manager or if you intend to
            start your own construction business someday, you will need to learn the appropriate
            skills and continue to hone your skills as a plumber.</p>
         <p>Apprenticeship is your first step down an exciting and challenging career path.
            Remember, every successful manager and business owner started as an apprentice.
            Successful plumbers have at least one thing in common: a willingness to keep on
            learning. That process of learning begins with apprentice training.</p>
      </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>
