<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><topic id="LP_topic_0" isTopic="true" xml:lang="english"><supertitle id="LpModuleNo">02101</supertitle><prolog/><body><title id="LpModuleTitle">Introduction to Plumbing</title></body><topic id="LP_topic_0_1" isTopic="true" xml:lang="english"><supertitle id="LpBookTitle">Plumbing</supertitle><body><title id="LpTitle">Lesson Plans for Instructors</title></body></topic><topic id="LP_topic_0_2" isTopic="true" xml:lang="english"><title sourcetype="practice" id="LpPerformanceTitle">Performance Tasks</title><body><section><p id="LpTeachingTime">Recommended Teaching Time: 5 hours</p></section><section><title id="LpResources">Resources</title><p><i>Plumbing a House</i>, 1998. Peter A. Hemp. Newtown, CT: Taunton Press.</p><p><i>The National Standard Plumbing Code</i>, Current edition. Falls Church, VA: Plumbing-Heating-Cooling Contractors Association.</p><p><i>Introduction to Hand Tools</i>, Module 00103, Latest Edition. NCCER. New York, NY: Pearson.</p><p><i>Introduction to Power Tools</i>, Module 00104, Latest Edition. NCCER. New York, NY: Pearson.</p><p>Council Tool website, www.counciltool.com.</p><p>The Stanley Tools website, www.stanleytools.com.</p></section></body></topic><topic id="LP_topic_0_3" isTopic="true" xml:lang="english"><supertitle id="LpSection">Section One</supertitle><body><title id="LpSectionTitle">The Plumbing Profession</title><section><title>Kickoff Activities</title><p>Have your trainees get into groups of three for three to four minutes and have each one discuss their interest in plumbing, prior experience, and knowledge they already have. Once the discussion is over, give them your background in plumbing and why you're teaching.</p></section><section><title>Sections 1.0.0–1.1.3</title><p>Describe how plumbing evolved from ancient times to modern times. </p></section><section><title>Teaching Tip</title><p>Select a few of the trade terms for Section 1.0.0 and write them on the board. Ask individual trainees to give broad definitions of the terms. Ask if there are any terms they would like to have further explained.</p></section><section><title>Sections 1.2.0–1.2.3</title><p>Describe the responsibilities of plumbers and discuss the other crafts that require similar skills, such as pipefitters and sprinkler fitters. Describe the types of work performed by plumbers.</p></section><section><title>Section 1.2.4–1.2.5</title><p>There are three phases of plumbing: underground rough-in, aboveground rough-in, and finish. Discuss the three phases and the importance of each phase.</p></section><section><title>Teaching Tip</title><p>Break students into three groups and assign each group one of the phases of a plumbing project. Have them determine what codes they would need to be prepared to know for their particular phase and how it impacts a job.</p></section><section><title>Wrap Up Activities</title><p>Exit Slip: have your students fill-out a notecard with one thing they learned and one question they have about plumbing after teaching section one.</p></section></body></topic><topic id="LP_topic_0_4" isTopic="true" xml:lang="english"><supertitle id="LpSection">Section Two</supertitle><body><title id="LpSectionTitle">Responsibilities of a Plumbing Professional</title><section><title>Sections 2.0.0–2.1.9</title><p>Describe the personal characteristics needed for someone to become successful.</p></section><section><title>Teaching Tip</title><p>Have trainees break into groups based on what they identify as their <i>weakest</i> quality out of the eight qualities a plumber must exhibit. Have them discuss ways in which they can improve this quality to become a well-rounded plumber.</p></section><section><title>Sections 2.2.0–2.2.6</title><p>Describe the range of opportunities available to someone who becomes a journey-level plumber. Explain the roles and responsibilities of different job positions in the industry. Explain how an apprentice program is structured and discuss the responsibilities of the apprentice and the sponsor</p></section><section><title>Wrap Up Activities</title><p>Based on the various career possibilities, ask individual trainees which one they think they might pursue in the long term and why they chose it. </p></section></body></topic><topic id="LP_topic_0_5" isTopic="true" xml:lang="english"><title id="LpReviewAndTesting">Review and Testing</title><body><section><title>Module Review</title><p>Have the trainees complete the Review Questions and Trade Terms Quiz at the end of the module. Alternatively, if this was assigned as homework, have them retrieve their answers for both assignments. Go over the answers to both assignments prior to administering the Module Examination. Ask the trainees if they need clarification of any particular knowledge areas.</p></section><section><title>Examination</title><p>Administer the Module Examination. Allow one to two minutes per test item for the written exam. Remind the trainees that they must answer at least 70 percent of the questions correctly to pass the Module Examination.</p></section><section><title>Wrap Up Activities</title><p>Ask the trainees if there were any trouble areas on the exam. Ask each trainee about their favorite and least favorite parts of the module. As an alternative or if time allows, briefly introduce the next topic in your planned teaching sequence.</p></section><section><title>Instructor</title><p>Record the testing results as required for paper-based exams. The results for exams administered through the Testing Management System are recorded automatically in the Registry System.</p></section></body></topic></topic>