<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<topic xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:nccer:names:ncs:xsd:NCS_topic.xsd" id="lp_warehouse_0001">
  <title id="frontmpref02.title">Warehouse Topic</title>
  <body>
    <section id="lp_intro">
      <p>Trainees with successful module completions may be eligible for credentialing through the
        NCCER Registry. To learn more, go to <xref href="www.nccer.org" format="html"
          scope="external">www.nccer.org</xref> or contact us at 1.888.622.3720. Our website has
        information on the latest product releases and training, as well as online versions of our
        Cornerstone magazine and Pearson’s product catalog.</p>
      <p>Your feedback is welcome. You may email your comments to <xref href="curriculum@nccer.org"
          format="html" scope="external">curriculum@nccer.org</xref>, send general comments and
        inquiries to <xref href="info@nccer.org" format="html" scope="external"
          >info@nccer.org</xref>, or fill in the User Update form at the back of this module.</p>
      <p>This information is general in nature and intended for training purposes only. Actual
        performance of activities described in this manual requires compliance with all applicable
        operating, service, maintenance, and safety procedures under the direction of qualified
        personnel. References in this manual to patented or proprietary devices do not constitute a
        recommendation of their use.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="lp_overview">
      <p>This Lesson Plan (LP) is divided into sections that correspond to the sections in the
        Trainee Guide module. As you plan your class times, review the objectives, content, and
        lesson plan outline for the section you plan to teach. Allow sufficient class time for
        demonstrations, laboratories, field trips, and testing. Each class period should also
        include time for administrative tasks and periodic breaks.</p>
      <p>Be sure to gather the required equipment, materials, visual aids, and answer keys. Using
        your access code, download the PowerPoint<sup>®</sup> presentations and Performance Sheets for this
        module from NCCER’s Instructor Resource Center at <xref href="www.nccerirc.com"
          format="html" scope="external">www.nccerirc.com</xref>.</p>
      <p>It is advisable to assign the reading of a module section prior to the classroom
        instruction. The Section Review and Module Review questions may be assigned as homework. At
        their discretion, instructors may assign additional homework to meet the teaching
        objectives.</p>
      <p>Performance Testing may be administered at any suitable time in the course of the module
        training. Tasks are graded pass/fail. Trainee performance and proficiency during practice
        sessions that meets or exceeds the standards for a task can be accepted as Performance Task
        completion. Complete the Performance Profile Sheet for each trainee.</p>
      <p>The final class is generally reserved for a brief review and the Module Examination. For
        information and updates about accessing the Module Examinations, visit
        <xref href="www.nccer.org/testing"
          format="html" scope="external">www.nccer.org/testing</xref>. The passing score for submission into NCCER’s Registry is 70% or
        above for the Module Exam. Record the testing results for each trainee on the Registration
        of Training Modules form and submit the form to the Training Program Sponsor.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="lp_prereqs">
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <p>None. Knowledge of previous levels is recommended.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="lp_safety">
      <title outputclass="t-wh">Safety Considerations</title>
      <p>This module will likely be taught exclusively in the classroom environment. However,
        instructors may teach or demonstrate portions of it in the shop or in the vicinity of
        functioning equipment. Electrical and mechanical safety must be emphasized at all times.
        Trainees should be carefully observed to ensure that they wear the proper PPE, follow safe
        practices, and give due respect to the hazards of energized and operating systems. Any work
        performed on functioning equipment must be completed under the direct supervision of the
        instructor.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="lp_equipment">
      <title outputclass="t-wh">Classroom Equipment and Materials</title>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>Whiteboard and markers</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Pencils and paper</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>PowerPoint<sup>®</sup> Presentations for Module 02101</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>A variety of standard marker sizes</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Poster board</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Flip chart</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>LCD projector and screen</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Computer with Internet access</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Module Review answer key</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Module Examinations</p>
        </li>
       
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="lp_resources">
      <p>There are a number of online resources available for trainees who would like more
        information about the module topic. A search for additional information may be assigned as
        homework to interested trainees.</p>
      <p>Instructors should view any videos that may be identified in the lesson plan before using
        them to ensure their suitability. The videos can provide examples of both proper and
        improper work processes and behaviors. Be prepared to stop the videos at appropriate times
        to point out and discuss both proper and improper conduct and techniques.</p>
      <p>Instructors are also encouraged to locate additional audiovisual aids available on the
        Internet, make personal videos, and take still pictures related to the subject matter and
        add them to the PowerPoint<sup>®</sup> presentations throughout the program.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="lp_safety2">
      <title>Safety Considerations</title>
      <p>This module is designed for classroom instruction. As a result, safety considerations are
        typically limited to that environment. Be sure to comply with any safety guidelines and
        policies of the host organization and facility, and emphasize the importance of wearing the
        required PPE any time trainees are in a shop or job-site environment.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="lp_instructional">
      <title outputclass="t-wh">Instructional Methods</title>
      <p>Instructional methods research has shown that varying instructional methods periodically
        throughout class sessions helps to engage and hold trainees’ attention. The PowerPoint<sup>®</sup>
        presentation that you received with this lesson plan is keyed to the sections of the Trainee
        Guide indicated below and has been designed for use with this Lesson Plan. </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
