<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><learningContent xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="M01_topic_2_2" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:nccer:names:ncs:xsd:NCS_learningContent.xsd" xml:lang="en">
   <title>1.2.0 Plumbing Today</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <lcInstruction>
         <p>Fresh water accounts for only about 3 percent of the water on Earth. In many places, the overuse of groundwater supplies has led to <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/aquifer_depletion">aquifer depletion</term>, the use of underground fresh water at a rate faster than it can be replenished. Many areas of the United States are dependent on aquifers such as the Ogallala, which stretches from Texas to South Dakota.</p>
      </lcInstruction>
      <section>
         <p>Moving into the twenty-first century, societies worldwide began to recognize the need to make wise use of natural resources, especially fresh water. The efforts to do so will continue to impact the plumbing profession for many years to come. Those efforts include practices such as <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/rainwater_harvesting">rainwater harvesting</term> (the collection and storage of rainwater for reuse), the reuse of <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/graywater">graywater</term> (laundry and bath water), and technologies such as the creation of a <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/bioswale">bioswale</term>, which is a constructed depression in the ground that filters pollutants from stormwater. Many places are also using <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/reclaimed_water">reclaimed water</term> for reuse in systems that are not meant for drinking, such as flushing fixtures. Reclaimed water has had impurities and solids removed from it.</p>
         <p>Founded in 1993, the non-profit <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/united_states_green_building_council_usgbc">United States Green Building Council (USGBC)</term> developed the <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/leadership_in_energy_and_environmental_design_leed">Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design (LEED)</term> green building certification system in 2000. LEED provides a way for contractors to identify and implement improved methods for the design, construction, operation, and maintenance of green buildings. Out of 110 possible points on the LEED rating scale, between 10 and 14 fall under the category of <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/water_efficiency">water efficiency</term>, or the managed use of drinkable water to reduce waste, with water management addressed in other categories as well. Both federal agencies and state governments have adopted LEED certification as a requirement for new construction, so it is important for plumbers to know and be able to work within these standards.</p>
         <p>In some areas of the country, plumbers are also responsible for installing and maintaining <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/geothermal">geothermal</term> (heated by energy from below the earth’s surface) and <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/solar_hot_water">solar hot water</term> (water that has been heated directly or indirectly by the sun) systems. Refer to your local applicable <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/code">code</term> to determine whether plumbers in your area install and maintain these systems.</p>
      </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>