<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><learningContent xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="M01_topic_3_1" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:nccer:names:ncs:xsd:NCS_learningContent.xsd" xml:lang="en">
   <title>2.1.0 Keys to Professional Success</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <lcInstruction>
         <p>Successful plumbers must be flexible enough to adapt their methods of working to the particular needs of each job. As you gain experience as a plumber, you will develop the flexibility necessary to meet changing job requirements. You will also improve your knowledge of the different tools and materials needed to accomplish certain jobs, and you will learn more about the technologies and methods that are available. Over time, you will improve your ability to do your job on time, on budget, and to the satisfaction of your customers. Satisfied customers mean repeat business.</p>
      </lcInstruction>
      <section>
         <p>Keep current with the latest methods, materials, and equipment in the plumbing profession. This knowledge will help you and the company you work for stay competitive. You should never stop learning. When you complete your apprenticeship, you will simply be moving into a bigger classroom: the world.</p>
         <p>Never take chances with your own safety or the safety of others. Always demonstrate a high level of professionalism. Remember, you are part of a proud heritage, and you represent a profession that is vital to modern society. As a plumber, you will want your customers to think well not only of your work as an individual, but also of the profession in general.</p>
         <p>Construction professionals adhere to a code of professional <term keyref="M01_trade_definitions/ethics">ethics</term>. Ethics are principles and values that guide conduct. As a plumber, you are responsible for understanding and following the code of ethics for your chosen profession. Appendix A lists the ethical principles that are followed by members of the construction trades.</p>
         <p>Successful plumbers exhibit all of the following qualities:</p>
      </section>
      <ul>
         <li>
            <p>Positive attitude</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Honesty</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Loyalty</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Willingness to learn</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Responsibility</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Cooperation</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Attentiveness to rules and regulations</p>
         </li>
         <li>
            <p>Promptness and reliability</p>
         </li>
      </ul>
      <section>
         <p>You were introduced to many of these concepts in the <i>Core Curriculum</i>. In this module, you will learn how they apply specifically to the plumbing trade. In the classroom and on the job, you will see that the successful plumbers you meet will demonstrate all of these qualities. Learn from them and become a better plumber.</p>
      </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>