<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?workdir /Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/maps/english/../../temp/ncs-epub23/topics/english?><?workdir-uri file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/maps/english/../../temp/ncs-epub23/topics/english/?><?path2project ../../../../?><?path2project-uri ../../../../?><?path2rootmap-uri ../../maps/english/?><learningContent xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dita-ot="http://dita-ot.sourceforge.net/ns/201007/dita-ot" id="M01_topic_3_2_1" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:nccer:names:ncs:xsd:NCS_learningContent.xsd" xml:lang="en" DITAArchVersion="1.2" class="- topic/topic learningBase/learningBase learningContent/learningContent " domains="(topic hi-d)           (topic indexing-d)          (topic ut-d)         (topic learningmeta-d)          (topic learningInteractionBase-d learning-d)          (topic learningBase+learningInteractionBase-d)         (topic learningBase+learningInteractionBase-d learningAssessment)         (topic learningBase+learningInteractionBase-d learningContent)           (topic learningBase+learningInteractionBase-d learningSummary)          (topic concept)          (topic reference)         (topic task)" xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="learningContent:1;4:32">
   <title class="- topic/title " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="title:1;5:11">2.2.1 Formal Construction Training</title>
   <learningContentbody class="- topic/body learningBase/learningBasebody learningContent/learningContentbody " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="learningContentbody:1;6:25">
      <lcInstruction class="- topic/section  learningBase/lcInstruction " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="lcInstruction:1;7:22">
         <p class="- topic/p " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="p:1;8:13">The Department of Labor’s Office of Apprenticeship sets the minimum standards for training programs across the country. Office of Apprenticeship programs rely on mandatory classroom instruction and OJL. Office of Apprenticeship requires 144 hours of classroom instruction per year and 2,000 hours of OJL per year. In a typical Office of Apprenticeship program, trainees spend 576 hours in classroom instruction and 8,000 hours in OJL before receiving journey plumber certificates.</p>
      </lcInstruction>
      <section class="- topic/section " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="section:1;10:16">
         <p class="- topic/p " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="p:2;11:13">To address the training needs of the professional communities, NCCER developed a four-year plumbing training program. NCCER uses the minimum Office of Apprenticeship standards as a foundation for comprehensive curricula that provide trainees with in-depth classroom and OJL experience.</p>
         <p class="- topic/p " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="p:3;12:13">The primary goal of NCCER is to standardize construction craft training throughout the country so that employers and employees benefit from it, no matter where they are located. As a trainee in an NCCER program, you receive benefits to help you prepare for your career in the plumbing profession. You will become part of the National Registry. You will receive a certificate for each level of training you complete. If you apply for a job with any participating contractor in the country, a transcript of your training will be available for that contractor to help verify your qualifications. If your training is incomplete when you make a job transfer, you can pick up where you left off, because every participating training center is using the same program. Many technical schools and colleges also use this program.</p>
         <p class="- topic/p " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="p:4;13:13">The NCCER Plumbing curriculum provides trainees with industry-driven training and education. It adopts a purely competency-based teaching philosophy. This means that trainees must demonstrate to the instructor that they possess the understanding and the skills necessary to complete the tasks that are covered in each module before they can advance to the next stage of the curriculum.</p>
         <p class="- topic/p " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="p:5;14:13">When the instructor is satisfied that a trainee has successfully demonstrated the required knowledge and skills for a particular module, test scores and completion information are sent to NCCER and kept in the National Registry. The National Registry can then confirm training and skills for workers as they move from state to state, company to company, or even within a company (see Appendix B).</p>
         <p class="- topic/p " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="p:6;15:13">Whether you enroll in an NCCER program or another Office of Apprenticeship -approved program, ensure that you work for an employer or sponsor who supports a nationally standardized training program that includes credentials to confirm your skill development.</p>
         <p class="- topic/p " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="p:7;16:13">A good apprenticeship program effectively combines competency-based, hands-on training with classroom instruction. This combination is the most effective way for a beginning plumber to learn and advance through the plumbing profession. Successful apprentices will develop the skills and knowledge they need to carry out a wide range of tasks.</p>
         <p class="- topic/p " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="p:8;17:13">If you possess these professional and personal skills, you can become a top-notch, highly productive journey plumber. Journey plumbers have successfully completed an apprenticeship-training program. The term comes from the fifteenth-century word journeyman. Journeymen were apprentices who left their masters after learning their craft and worked alone or for someone else.</p>
         <p class="- topic/p " xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/topics/english/M01_topic_3_2_1.xml" xtrc="p:9;18:13">Successful journey plumbers who practice their craft with pride and skill are valued employees and co-workers. Once you have mastered the professional and personal skills necessary, you will be a good candidate to advance to an exciting and challenging career as a master plumber, superintendent plumber, plumbing supervisor, instructor, inspector, project manager, or contractor and business owner.</p>
      </section>
   </learningContentbody>
<related-links class="- topic/related-links "><linkpool class="- topic/linkpool " xtrc="topicref:30;49:75" xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/maps/english/02101.ditamap"><link class="- topic/link " format="dita" href="../../topics/english/M01_topic_3_2.xml" mapclass="- map/topicref " role="parent" scope="local" type="learningContent" xtrc="topicref:29;48:69" xtrf="file:/Users/gpage/Documents/Content/ncs_content/9780130210100/maps/english/02101.ditamap"><?ditaot usertext?><linktext class="- topic/linktext "><?ditaot gentext?>2.2.0 Career Opportunities in Plumbing</linktext></link></linkpool></related-links></learningContent>